# Vivekpandian Veerapandian

San Jose, CA (214) 802-4843 github.com/vivekpandian08

vivekpandian08.github.io
linkedin.com/in/vivekpandian8

vivekpandian08@gmail.com medium.com/@vivekpandian08

**Data Scientist** with **4 years of experience** in extracting customer and marketing insights from data points by building Linear and Non-Linear ML models. Established a \$25k revenue E-commerce business by recommending data-driven solutions.

#### **EDUCATION**

The University of Texas at Dallas - M.S., Business Analytics (Data Science Specialization), 3.67

Jan 2019 – Dec 2020

 Mentored 15 Grad Students for ML Project competition, and secured 3rd place. Built end to end regression model, developed web app using FLASK that predicts house price and hosted the app in the cloud using AWS.

College of Engineering Guindy, India - B.E., Electronics and Communication

Aug 2007 – May 2011

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

**SuperWorld**, United States – Augmented Reality Real Estate on Blockchain

**Data Science Intern** | R

Sept 2020 – Present

• Developed an interactive web app in R-shiny that does real-time end to end sentiment analysis of SuperWorld's tweets

Ordermycake.in, India – E-Commerce B2C Platform to sell Bakery Products

Senior Data Scientist | Python, Tableau, AWS EC2, S3

Oct 2016 - June 2018

- Generated 18% increase in revenue to \$5k in 2017 by leveraging NLP techniques to analyze customers feedback
- Recommended optimized price for products by web scraping and data mining to analyze competitor product prices,
   leading to a \$3K increase in yearly revenue
- Designed 3 A/B tests to identify the most engaging marketing campaign, resulted in a 30% increase in sales and examined
   8 layouts and designs, increased Add to Cart rate to 40%
- Led a 10-member cross-functional team to build an end to end B2C platform to expand the **operations from 2 to 8 cities** and presented reports to stakeholders using **Tableau** charts and dashboards

Data Scientist | R, Python

Jan 2015 – Sep 2016

- Identified **4500 potential churn customers** by developing ML models using Logistic Regression, Decision Tree and **mitigated 36%** by offering them discounts
- Initiated a new payment method to solve delivery problems that satisfied customers and increased unit sales to 6.5%
- Revamped coupon mailing strategy for 3 customer segments by clustering using **K-means** and identifying the most engaging coupons leading to a **12% estimated increase in headcount**
- Built machine learning pipelines using python, optimized XGBoost model by adding new features to improve precision rate to 76% for the likelihood of purchase by analyzing consumer behavior

- Designed SQL queries to extract information from IoT sensor data and identified anomalies by K-means clustering
- Analyzed product pain points and collaborated with a multi-functional team to develop robust solutions to meet client requirements, increased project conversion to 30%

## PERSONAL PROJECTS (MACHINE LEARNING)

Can I predict your food? Maybe I Can! | Android SDK, Python (Deep Learning, GPU)

Sept 2020 – Present

- Gathering food images using JavaScript Console Window and python, and labeling by "LabelImg" annotation tool
- Building a prototype that takes data from users and does end to end ML to classify foods using TensorFlow Lite

**Uber Tweet Analysis** | Python (Natural Language Processing, Unsupervised Learning)

Mar 2020 – July 2020

Data mined 5 years Uber tweets using Tweepy, stored in MongoDB, cleaned and processed data by establishing an ETL pipeline, and identified 3 key topics that customer mentioning using LDA algorithm and achieved coherence score of 0.36

**Credit Card Fraud Detection** | Python (Supervised Learning)

May 2019 – July 2019

 Performed quantitative analysis, and hypothesis testing. Built an ML pipeline in PySpark to predict fraud transaction using SVM, KNN, Naïve Bayes Random Forest, and Neural Networks with SMOTE resampling and achieved AUC of 0.82

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Programming: Python (Scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, Spacy, PySpark), R, SQL, SAS

Visualization: Tableau, Power BI, Shiny, Plotly, Streamlit

Databases & Bigdata: Snowflake, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, MongoDB (NoSQL), Hadoop, Hive, Spark